Whyte, William Foote Office Records /4058
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
William Foote Whyte Office Records
1947-1977
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Whyte, William Foote.
/4058
4 cubic feet
4 linear ft.
Records (documents).
7980435
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
C. Tan, June 17, 2011
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, September 23, 2016
Biographical / Historical
William Foote Whyte (June 27, 1914-July 16, 2000) was a sociologist chiefly known for his ethnographic study in urban sociology, Street Corner Society. Whyte, from an upper middle class background, showed an early interest in writing, economics and social reform. After graduating from Swarthmore College, he was selected for the Junior Fellows program, where his landmark research was done. After his research in Boston, he entered the sociology doctoral program at the University of Chicago. Street Corner Society was published by the University of Chicago Press in 1943. He spent a year teaching at the University of Oklahoma, but developed polio in 1943 and spent two years in physical therapy at the Warm Springs Foundation. Rehabilitation was only partially successful; Whyte walked with a cane for the rest of his life, and used two arm crutches in his later years. He briefly returned to the University of Chicago in 1944, then joined the New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations at Cornell University in 1948, remaining at Cornell for the remainder of his career. He worked for social reform and social change, directing his efforts toward "empowering the disenfranchized and narrowing the gap between rich and poor." He studied industrial and agricultural workers and workers' cooperatives in Venezuela, Peru, Guatemala and in the Basque region of Spain, as well as in the United States. He authored hundreds of articles and 20 books including an autobiography. He is considered a pioneer in industrial sociology.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /4087: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4094: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4102: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4149: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4151: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4149 AV: "ASA Award Presentation to William Foote Whyte by Jacqueline Scheier" Audio-Visual Materials /4168: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4173: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers
Whyte, William Foote, 1914-2000
7980435
- Dunkirk Institute Reports, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Moore Business Forms Plant, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Fairport Report, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Moore Interviews, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Moore Business Forms 2nd Supervisory Training Course, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- MBF 2nd Supervisory Training Course Final Report of Meetings, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Money & Motivation, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Human Relations Research in Corning Glass Works- Whyte, Miller, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Pattern for Ind Peace, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Elmira Release to Papers re: Fairport, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Core Course-Field Methods Interviewing, etc. Whyte, Richardson, Macmillan, Dean, etc. (1 of 2), 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Core Course-Field Methods Interviewing, etc. Whyte, Richardson, Macmillan, Dean, etc. (2 of 2), 1952 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Design for Experiment, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Bradford A Group, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Lee Bradford's A Group, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- A Group Report members, perceptions, and questions, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Lee Bradford's A Group Meeting Reports, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Class Cases, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Training Materials, 1949-1952 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Interview with Al Wagner, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Remington Rand Union Officers, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- A Group Report, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- HR Debates, 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- T-Borg Research Meetings (1 of 2), 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- T-Borg Research Meetings (2 of 2), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Outline of Productivity Volume, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Proposed Curriculum, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Salaries, 1947-1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Instituto de Estudios Peruanos, 1959-1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- National Science Foundation, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- IEP Correspondence, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- IEP Correspondence, 1969-1974 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Dean McConnell, 1959-1962 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Member Structured Conference and Group Dynamics, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- HR Research Meetings, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- NIMH Project #6198, 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Dean Catherwood, 1954-1958 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Peruvian Government, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Cornell-CAL Relationship, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Creole Petroleum Corporation, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Creole, 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Obstetrical Service, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Housing of Creole Workers, 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Progress Reports on Whyte's Project, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Creole-Caracas, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- General-Bolivar District, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Creole Correspondence (1 of 2), 1955 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Creole Correspondence (2 of 2), 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- National Science Foundation (1 of 2), 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- National Science Foundation (2 of 2), 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Dr. Jose Matos (1 of 2), 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Dr. Jose Matos (2 of 2), 1964-1967 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Teaching Course Materials, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Teaching Course Materials, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Human Problems of U.S. Enterprise in Latin America Spring Summer Institute, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- ILR Case Material, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Teaching Cases (1 of 2), 1951 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Teaching Cases (2 of 2), 1950-1954 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- ILR 420 Experimental Course on Group Processes (1 of 3), 1959 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- ILR 420 Experimental Course on Group Processes (2 of 3), 1959 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- ILR 420 Experimental Course on Group Processes (3 of 3), 1959 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Agency for International Development, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Agency for International Development, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Agriculture Development Council Account, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Agriculture Development Council, Inc. Report for 1975, 1971-1975 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Brian Tucker, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  Scope and Contents
  Fall 1975
- Roca Santiago, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Mami Mizele, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Don Lifton, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- David Leslie, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Art Hansen, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Access, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Marco Ferroni, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Richard Weiss, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Rutgers, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Perry: Dirty Work, Clean Jobs, Proud Men, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Gerald Gordon, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Official Letters (1 of 2), 1966-1976 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Official Letters (2 of 2), 1962-1966 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Systems Research Working Paper Series, 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- The Puebla Project, 1967-1973 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- On the Future of the Social Sciences at Cornell, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Organizational Behavior Research, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 3)